<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of the Commissioners of the Navie, to a scandalous pamphlet, published by Mr Andrewes Burrell.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Commissioners of the Admiralty and the Navy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E340_31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861513</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113650</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75398)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113650)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E340[31])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of the Commissioners of the Navie, to a scandalous pamphlet, published by Mr Andrewes Burrell.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Commissioners of the Admiralty and the Navy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Will. Bentley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. MDCXLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A reply to. Burrell, Andrewes. To the Right Honourable, the High Court of Parliament, the humble remonstrance of Andrewes Burrell Gent. (Wing B5973).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 18th London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burrell, Andrewes. --  To the Right Honourable, the High Court of Parliament, the humble remonstrance of Andrewes Burrell Gent.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Naval operations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113650:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113650:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER OF THE COMMISSIONERS of the NAVIE, To a ſcandalous Pamphlet, publiſhed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ANDREWES, BURRELL.</p>
            <p>Printed by WILL. BENTLEY, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> MDCXLVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113650:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113650:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the High Court of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome dayes paſt, there came to the hands of us the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Navie, a Pamphlet, publiſhed in print by <hi>Andrewes Burrell,</hi> concerning the Navie, (a buſineſſe then depending before the Honourable Committee of the Admiralty.) We much wondered at the boldneſſe in the manner of ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, and at the Scandals, through the whole body of the Pamphlet; he daring to direct it unto your Honours; and therein ſcandalizing the Navie-royall of the kingdom, and all the Officers of the ſame; as Admirals, Vice-Admirals, and Rear-Admirals, Commiſſioners, Collectors, Trinity-houſe, and others; yea, and beyond this, ſome of your Members, and in truth, the honour of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>We are confident thoſe aſperſions and brain-ſick Notions, ſo plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his diſcontentedneſſe, and ſelf-ends, and ſo apparently tending to the deſtruction of the Royall Navie, will not get the leaſt credit with your Honours: But, leſt this Pamphlet ſhould work ſuch ill effect abroad, that after your Honours happy government, protection, and defence of this Kingdom, in theſe Civill Broils, by the Navie Royall, as with Walls and Bulworks, from all forraign Invaſion; your Honours proceedings ſhould upon this mans writing be calumniated, by the diſaffected party here at home; and your Royall Navie, (formerly ſo formidable) become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to forraign States and Princes: and we knowing that the great affairs of State will not afford time unto your Honours, to take a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular examination of this buſineſſe, to the diſcovery of the folly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate malice of this Gentl. and we being intruſted by your Honours in the government and care of the Navie Royall, have thought it not the leaſt part of our duties, to make bold, by our Anſwer unto this Pamphlet, to preſent unto your Honours the true ſtate of the Navie, to diſcover the deſtructive effects ſo much aimed at, and deſired to the Navie in the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, to ſtop the mouths of Enemies and ill-affected, to ſatisfie the well-affected, and to vindicate the honour of the Parliament, whoſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and prudent care for preſervation of the Navie, and guarding of the Seas, in theſe times of danger, we ſhall make appear to exceed all former Ages.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113650:3"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Maſter</hi> Burrell, <hi>in the beginning of his Preface, begins to tell a Story, That he was forced out of his Countrey, for his affection to the Parliament, and of his taking the Covenant, and of being preſſed every Lords day to diſcover what he knew to be advantageous or hurtfull to the Parliament; when indeed and in truth, the one was, becauſe he would contribute little or nothing to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, having lived here a long time obſcurely; and the other, becauſe for his private advantage and advance of his Fortunes, he would be an Officer of the Navie: But at laſt, being rowſed up (as he ſaith) by Church-men, he complained to the Right Honourable the Lord</hi> Say, <hi>the Navie was ſluggiſh, and did ſail ſo ſluggiſhly, that it could not perform thoſe Services which the Parliament expected; and to that purpoſe preſented a paper to his Lordſhip, intituled,</hi> Obſervations upon the Navie, by <hi>Andrews Burrell: which paper he preſented to the Earl of</hi> Warwick, <hi>and from his Lordſhip it was ſent to be diſputed before us the Commiſsioners of the Navie, with whom (ſaith he) it died.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Now may it pleaſe the honourable Houſes of Parliament, That it is true, we received an Order from the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> as alſo from the Honourable Committee of the Navie, to ſend for Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> to hear his opinion concerning the reducing of the Navie into a better poſture, as he pretended, for ſailing: We likewiſe ſent for all the Maſter Shipwrights of <hi>England,</hi> Captain <hi>Batten</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with us. Being come together, we demanded of Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> in what manner he would do this great work: His Anſwer was, He would cut them down to one Tire of Ordnance, by which means they ſhould ſail a great deal better. We demanded of him, What he would do to adde quality to them; for in cutting them down, without doing ſomething under water, would be to ſmall purpoſe: His Anſwer was, That he would keep that private to himſelf. We deſired him to give it in writing how he would perform this Service, if he did make a triall of one of the old Ships, in regard it would be a great charge to the State; which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to do, but never came near the Office more, nor ever heard we more of him, till now, that he hath ſet out this Scandalous Libell. And indeed what he propounded to us, which was to cut down the firſt, ſecond, and third Rate-Ships, and to bring them to one Tire of Ordnance, is ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and will ſo diſable the Navie, that it will make them, in caſe of forraign invaſion in capable either to offend the Enemy, or defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; all other Princes Ships of the firſt, ſecond, and third Rate, having two or three Tire of Ordnance. Beſides, as they are now built, having great Floors, and great Breadths, if they ſhould be cut down, they would be ſo unruly Ships in the Sea, that in a Sea-gate they would roul ſo much, that no man would be able to ply the Ordnance, or ſtand upon the Deck. Beſides, if they ſhould meet with a Storm, be in danger to roul their Maſts by the Board, as appeared by the <hi>Rainbow,</hi> and <hi>Vantguard,</hi> which were built
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113650:3"/>in 86. little more or leſſe: after this Modell proved ſo defective Ships in the Sea, that they were forced to bring on another Deck upon them: The <hi>Victorie,</hi> in 87, was cut down for a triall, at the inſtance of Sir <hi>Iohn Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings,</hi> from three Decks and an half, to one Tire of great Ordnance; which being done, the Queen commanded, in 88, that he ſhould go Commander of her, becauſe he was the Projector; but when he came up to the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Ships with two Tire and three Tire of Ordnance, they tore his Ship, and kill'd his men ſo faſt that he was not able to endure the <hi>Spaniards</hi> broad Sides, but was forced to leave them; So that when the Ship came home, the Queens Majeſtie underſtanding how much the Ship was diſabled by cutting down her Decks, gave Order for her Decks to be built again; and ever after ſhe carried two Tire of Ordnance fore and aft. And indeed the Ships of the Navie, of the firſt and ſecond Rate, are the beſt built Ships in the World, both for defence and offence, carrying two Tire of Ordnance; and if not laden with Victuals, but kept light and clean, will ſaile as well as any Ships of their burthen and force that do belong to any Chriſtian Prince, having been a terror to their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; witneſſe <hi>Anno</hi> 88. for if there had not been ſuch Ships at that time, but ſuch reformed Ships as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> endevoureth to have, the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> doubtleſſe had overrun them, and with their ſtrength of Ordnance, having two and three Tire, would have been too hot for their coming near them: yet ſuch was the ſtrength of our Ships, moſt of them having two Tire of Ordnance, and well mann'd, that (by the bleſſing of God) we gave them the overthrow: And ever ſince the Navie hath been preſerved and built in a better poſture then in thoſe dayes, and more ſerviceable for the honour and preſervation of the Kingdom. And becauſe your Honours may be ſatisfied, how neceſſary great Ships are with two Tire of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, for the defence of this Kingdom, we ſhall onely inſtance in two Ships which are yet lively in our memory. In <hi>Anno</hi> 1640. <hi>Don Antonio de Kendo</hi> came into the Downs, with a Fleet of Ships from <hi>Spain,</hi> and having rid there ſome time, the Admirall <hi>Van Trump,</hi> with ſix of the beſt Ships in <hi>Holland,</hi> attended the motion of <hi>Don Antonio</hi> his Ship; the reſt of his Fleet, conſiſting of eighty Sail, attended the reſt of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet: <hi>Don Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> when he had refreſhed his men, and fitted himſelf, weighed Anchor out of the Downs; the Admirall of <hi>Holland</hi> did the like with ſix Ships; and coming without the <hi>Goodwyn-Sands,</hi> the Admirall of <hi>Holland</hi> came up with the Admirall of <hi>Spain,</hi> as far as his tranſome; but received ſuch entertainment, that he durſt never more come up with him, nor any of the Ships in his company, notwithſtanding the Admirall of <hi>Spain</hi> ſtayed for them with his top-Sails down, and main yard a croſſe; ſuch great force had this great Ship with two Tire and an half of Ordnance, that the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> durſt not deal with her. The Admirall of <hi>Portugall,</hi> being another great Ship of that Fleet with two Tire of Ordnance, fought with ſixteen
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113650:4"/>States Men of War almoſt a whole day, yet never could take her, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offered any quarter that they would demand, ſcorned it: At laſt, when the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſaw they could not take her, two of their Men of War deſperately ran aboard of her, with two Fire-Ships, where they all burned together, untill they were conſumed. And indeed, if they had not uſed that Stratagem, they had never deſtroyed her. By this, your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours may perceive the great difference between Ships of two Tire of Ordnance, and one Tire, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> would have them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place he makes a long Narration of the</hi> Sally-<hi>Fleet, where Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> Rainsborow <hi>was Commander, and ſaith, He findes in his Iournall theſe words,</hi> (We did give them chaſe all day, and at night we loſt them:) <hi>which great deficiency (ſaith he) renders the Navie to be in a contemptible condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Now let any Sea-man judge, whether Captain <hi>Rainſhorow</hi>'s Fleet could be in a fit condition, to chaſe light and clean Veſſels that came out of <hi>Sally</hi> that night, when he had been two Moneths from <hi>England,</hi> and grown foule, and four Months Victuals in: Beſides, thoſe ſmall Veſſels which he chaſed, were (when he firſt ſaw them) two Leagues from him, which was a long chaſe to fetch up, and would hold a good Sailor chaſing all day: Beſides, if the Men of War had contemned them, (as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith,) why did they run from them, and would not fight? For by their running away, it is evident they were not contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but feared: And yet he confeſſeth, that Fleet performed better Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, then <hi>Englands</hi> Navie did in 44 years before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, (becauſe we will touch onely what concerns our ſelves) Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>diſcovers where the fault hath been, That the Navie hath not been reformed, and how the Right Honourable the Earl of</hi> Warwick, <hi>hath been miſled by the Officers of the Navie, and the Brethren of the Trinity-houſe, who ſhould have adviſed his Lordſhip to make choice of nimble Ships for Warlike Service: &amp; that if the Brethren of the Trinity-houſe were ſo knowing as they ſeem, and ſo well affected as they ought, they ſhould have ſent forth for their own Adventure, one Ship and one Pinace, that ſhould have ſailed as nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as the Queens Ship: Such an example (ſaith he) peradventure would have moved the dull Officers, to hearken to the reducing of part of the Navie into a ſerviceable poſture for theſe times, and to make choice of better Ships, which they have hired at dearer Rates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Anſwer</hi> thereunto, We wonder much at the boldneſſe of this ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brained man, that he ſhould queſtion the judgement of that noble Earl to be miſled by us, as if his Lordſhip were not a Sea-man himſelf, to diſcern what is fit to be done, for the making of fit and nimble Ships for Service, better then Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> who ſcarce ever ſaw ſalt water, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently never ſaw Service. And for the affection of the Trinity-houſe, we are confident, that divers of that Corporation, have ſet out many Ships
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113650:4"/>and Pinaces, for the Publike, in theſe diſtracted times, to their great loſſe and hinderance, as ſome of the Members of the honourable Houſe of Commons can witneſſe: but never heard that Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> nor his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates, ſet out any Ship or Pinace, in defence of the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſince theſe Wars began. And for the reducing of the Navie into ſuch a poſture as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> would have it; we hope never to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo great a disſervice to this Kingdom: And although Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> ſaith, we have made bad choice of Ships, and at dear rates, to ſerve the State; we ſhall make it appear to the honourable Houſes, that they have been the beſt Merchants Ships in this Kingdom, and taken up at no other rates, then hath been given long before we came in Office, in the moſt peaceable times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Folio</hi> 4, <hi>Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>quarrels with the Trinity-houſe, and talks of Toles and fair Immunities coming in by the induſtrious Sea-men, and chalks them out their duty to take care for the common Sea-men, and not to ſuffer thouſands of them in diſcontent to run out of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As for the Toles and Immunities, which the Trinity-houſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, they receive it with one hand, and pay it with the other, to the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and fatherleſſe of that Corporation, and to ſuch as have received wounds and hurts, in the Parliaments and Merchants Service; for which they have two pence a voyage out of every common Sea-man, and no more if the voyage be three years long; yet the malice of Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> would make the world beleeve, the Trinity-houſe receives much, when indeed their whole comings in (ſince theſe diſtracted times) doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve half the poor belonging to that Corporation. And for the common Sea-men, they need not be diſcontented, having had an Augmentation of four ſhillings in a Moneth more then ever any King or Queen in <hi>England</hi> gave them, beſides other Immunities granted them by the Parliament: Neither do we beleeve that any are gone over, except ſuch as are Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Enemies to the State, which are better out of the Kingdom, then in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, he roves by way of Multiplication, in which, it ſeems, he is not skilfull, for inſtead of</hi> 500, <hi>he ſaith, the Officers of the Navie ſent out their Preſt-maſters into</hi> Suffolk <hi>and</hi> Eſſex, <hi>to preſſe</hi> 900 <hi>Sea-men, and out of the River of</hi> Thames, 200 <hi>Water-men; but at the day of their appearing, of all that number, there appeared at</hi> Chatham <hi>but</hi> 224, <hi>whereof</hi> 124 <hi>were Water-men: and then makes his Inference, as if there were a ſcarcity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe in Sea-men, and Water-men, to the Service of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which we <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That we did ſend out Preſt-maſters to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid places for 500 men, and not for 900, (as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> falſely ſaith) to the end we might not make a ſcarcity of men in this City for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Ships, in regard we were to ſet out a Fleet of 6000 men, whereas in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113650:5"/>time paſt our predeceſſors for ſuch Fleets, never preſt leſſe then 2000 men in the Countrey: yet ſuch was the willingneſſe of the Sea-men and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-men, to ſerve the Parliament, that the Ships are all mann'd long ſince, and at Sea; and we writ our Letters down to the Preſt-maſters to ſtay their hand; and of thoſe that were preſſed, came to <hi>Chatham</hi> (as appears under the Clerk of the Checks hand) 358 men, beſides Water-men. By this the honourable Houſes of Parliament may perceive the malice of this Gentleman, who not onely ſtrives to blaſt your faithfull Servants, but as much as in him lies, ſeeks to bring the honourable Houſes in a diſlike with the common Sea-men, that ſo ſome rigid courſes may be taken againſt thoſe that hitherto have done them faithfull Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, he falls foul of the Ship that carried over the Queens Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and inſerts ſome words in Captain</hi> Battens <hi>Letter to the Parliament in theſe words; If my life and all the Kingdom had lain at Stake, I could not prevent her going over, for (ſaith he) the Ship that carried her, ſailes two foot for my one. Then he makes his inference, and would have Captain</hi> Batten <hi>ſpeak in his own language, as if he would have ſaid (ſaith he) that other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can make nimble Ships, but</hi> England <hi>is grown dull, and muſt be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſluggiſh and unſerviceable Ships. Then he further addes, that if the Parliament had ſpent every year a million of Pounds, they that have waſted one million in three years, would not of themſelves have endevoured to build or purchaſe one Ship or Pinace fo nimble as the Queens Ship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By this your Honours may perceive, he ſtill hammers upon one Anvill, that is, as much as in him lies, to diſparage the Navie-Royall, and to infuſe into Strangers minds how unſerviceable they are, that ſo he might blaſt the honour and reputation of the whole Navie, which hath been and is both famous and terrible to all Nations; and onely for this cauſe, that ſo great a Ship as the Saint <hi>Andrew,</hi> being foul at that time, could not fetch up a clean tallowed Frigate, new come out of Port, having the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the wind, and being a ſpeciall Sailor, and fitted for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to carry away the Queen. And for the ſpending of ſo much money, we know it is far ſhort of that Sum; yet thus much we dare aver, that if theſe times be compared with precedent times when ſuch Fleets have been ſet forth, the honourable Houſes will find by the Accompts, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more frugality was uſed, then ſince the Parliament had the Navie in their hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place he ſaith, he was unexpectedly nominated a Commiſsioner for the Sale of Prizes and Prize-goods, and ſaith, he would have attended the Service faithfully; but at his entrance into that truſt, he was unfitly oppoſed in the Sale of a nimble Pinace, which by a ſtrong hand was eſtranged from the Parliament, without Candle-light: and being ſo oppoſed, he was much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, becauſe he knew himſelf beſt able to ſerve the Parliament; and thereupon deſiſted, and came no more amongſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113650:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That it is true, he was nominated a Commiſſioner for Prizes, and Prize-goods, but not unexpectedly, for he expected 300. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> but after he had ſat two or three dayes with us, and heard that we were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing but our labour for our pains: truly he then very unfitly left us, and never ſat more amongſt us. And for being oppoſed in the ſale of a nimble Pinace, which by a ſtrong hand was eſtranged from the Parliament; we wonder that all this time he hath not diſcovered it; that ſo thoſe perſons may be puniſhed according to their demerits: and therefore we humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the honourable houſes of Parliament, to cauſe this buſineſſe to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and that Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> do diſcover what Pinace that was, and who it was that eſtranged her from the Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith, That before and ſince that time ſome nimble Ships and many Pinaces have been taken, but moſt of them by diſaſters; and if thoſe Ships and Pinaces had been contrived into Men of War, and ſet out in the room of thoſe ſluggiſh Ships which he complains of, the Parliament would have been much better ſerved, with the ſaving half of that vaſt charge which hath been ſpent at Sea; yet ſaith he, it is certain the beſt of thoſe Ships and Pinaces, have been eſtranged from the Parliament, which makes the abuſe the greater, and therefore makes a quere to examine what price was paid the Parliament for</hi> Plunkets <hi>Ship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It ſeems now Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> will confeſſe that ſome nimble Ships and Pinaces have been taken by the Parliament Ships, but yet to eclipſe the taking of them, he ſaith, Moſt of them were taken by diſaſters, which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to be true; for it was a diſaſter befell them that were taken. And as for thoſe ſhips that were taken, they that were good Sailors, and fit to be made men of Warre were fitted and equipped, and are now in the ſervice of the Parliament to the number of ſeven good Ships, and ſixteen Frigates, and not eſtranged from the Parliament, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſets forth, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe will ſave charges, in regard the Parliament payes not fraight, though not half the charge, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith: And as for Captain <hi>Plunkets</hi> Ship, if Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> had inquired of Maſter <hi>Morris Thomſon,</hi> amongſt other things he would have told him that ſhe was ſtranded about <hi>Arundell</hi> by five States-men of warre, and ſeized on by Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> army, and condemned in the Admiraltie as Prize to Maſter <hi>Thompſon</hi> and others for loſſes received by the Dunkirkers, ſo that as we conceive nothing was due to the Parliament; yet we humbly deſire the honourable Houſes, to examine Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> becauſe he ſaith, It is certain that the beſt of thoſe Ships and Pinaces were eſtranged, that he may declare in whoſe hands thoſe Ships and Pinaces are, that ſo the Parliament may be righted, and the offenders receive condigne puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place in his old ridiculous ſtrain, he falls a praiſing of</hi> Plunkets <hi>Ship for failing, although he never ſaw her ſail, and dispraiſing of the great new Frigate before he knows what ſhe wil be, as he doth all the reſt of the Navie:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113650:6"/>Then he falls to telling of a ſtory, and ſaith, he believes that all the Ships in the Navie in three years have not taken ſo many Prizes, as</hi> Plunkets <hi>Ship hath taken in theſe two years, and that ſome of thoſe Prizes were very rich, but by eſtranging that Ship of</hi> Plunkets, <hi>the Parliament hath loſt all thoſe Prizes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Your Honours may perceive what Maſter <hi>Burrells</hi> intentions are by his language; that is, ſtill to diſhonour the Royall Navie, calling them ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh, and praiſing of <hi>Flunkets</hi> Frigate for a nimble Saylor, when there is twentie ſail of Frigates and Ships now in the Parliament ſervice, that fail as well, and many of them better. And whereas he falſely ſaith, that <hi>Plunkets</hi> Ship hath taken more Prizes in two years, then the Parliament Ships have taken in three; we ſhall referre your Honours to the Collectours for Prizes, and Prize-goods; and they will tell your Honours that the Parliament Ships have taken a hundred and ten Merchant Ships, and thirty nine Men of War have been taken and ſunk, which had his Majeſties Commiſſion; beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Spaniards, French, and Dutch that have been delivered back at the earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt requeſt of the Ambaſſadours. And we never heard of more then ſix Ships taken by Captain <hi>Plunckets</hi> Frigate, and moſt of them being Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Ships.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, he begins a large diſcourſe, that in November laſt, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that there was three Frigates to be built for the State, and that he was deſigned to build one; and was ſhewed a paper from a principall Ship-wright, which be had received from the Officers of the Navie, directing him how he ſhould build one of the Frigats, that when ſhe was built, ſhe would never do any good ſervice: but ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Burrell, <hi>that which troubled the Ship-wright moſt, was the price; for (ſaith he) if they give a ſlight price, they muſt expect ſlight Frigates. Then (ſaith Maſter</hi> Burrell) <hi>I took the paper into conſideration, and I acquainted the Ship-wright with my diſlike of it, and told him I would move the Lords of the Admiraltie ſo to order the buſineſſe, that thoſe Ship-wrights that did build them, ſhould build without direction from the Officers of the Navy: and that they ſhould have an indifferent price for them, which was that which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Burrell <hi>aimed at, becauſe he would build one: Then he ſets forth the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and form of his Petition to the Lords of Admiralty in two ſides of paper, and tells their Lordſhips of ten Whelps built by the direction of Sir</hi> Iohn Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton; <hi>and rakes up the aſhes of his dead body, and ſaith, the builders were ſo miſled by him, that all thoſe veſſels proved ſluggiſh. Then he layes down poſitive rules and directions, how the Frigates ſhould be built, as punctually, as</hi> Archime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <hi>the Mathematician, but ſtill hath a care of his intereſt, and deſires that the Builders might not be diſheartned in the price of them. Then he propounds</hi> 300l. <hi>to be depoſited, that is to ſay, to each builder an</hi> 100 l. <hi>and the Frigates to ſail into Downs, and from thence to the Iſle of Wight, and then round about the Iſland, and ſo to</hi> Portſ-mouth; <hi>and that Frigate that cometh in there firſt, to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſt Frigate for ſervice, and that the Ship-wright that built her, ſhould have the</hi> 300 l. <hi>for his ſervice. Then (ſaith he) before I offered theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113650:6"/>to their Lordſhips: I conferred with Maſter</hi> Pet, <hi>and Maſter</hi> Caſtle, <hi>whether they were willing to build two of the Frigates, upon the forementioned tearms, or not, and if they would build each of them one, be would build the third: So when I found (ſaith he) Maſter</hi> Pet <hi>and Maſter</hi> Caſtle <hi>to like my propoſitions, I preſented them to the Honourable Earle of</hi> Warwick, <hi>and Lord</hi> Say, <hi>and proved before their Lordſhips, that if the Frigates were built, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the directions of the Officers of the Navie, the Frigates would prove unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the State: But (ſaith Maſter</hi> Burrell) <hi>this took no effect. Soon after came forth other directions worſe then the firſt, That one of the intended Frigates ſhould be built</hi> 70 <hi>Tons bigger then the other two, whereas by my propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions they ſhould be all of equall burden: And ſecondly, Maſter</hi> Pet <hi>Iunior, ſhould build the bigger, and Maſter</hi> Pet <hi>ſenior the two leſſer Frigates, by which ſubtile plot (ſaith he) all emulation was laid aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer to the needfull, of what Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> hath falſely ſuggeſted: In the firſt place, your Honours may perceive what Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> drives at: the firſt is a good price, not for the good of the Kingdome, but for his own ends: becauſe (ſaith he) I was deſigned by their Lordſhips to build one. In the next place, he would brand the Commiſſioners of the Navie, in giving di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the building of unſerviceable Frigates, when indeed they gave no directions for them, but gave the Maſter Ship-wright order, to draw out their own dimenſions, which accordingly they did, which we have ready to produce under their hands: And if the ten Whelps built many years ſince proved deficient, it doth not follow theſe Frigates now a building, ſhould prove no better Saylors. But Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> in that ſtrikes at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Navie, wounding us through Sir <hi>Iohn Penningtons</hi> ſides, as if theſe Frigates would be unſerviceable, becauſe he falſely ſuggeſts, we gave directions therein: And for his propoſitions to try their Sailing round about the Ile of <hi>Wight</hi> to <hi>Portſmouth</hi> is ſo ridiculous that we need not trouble our ſelves about it, for all Sea-men know that there can be no triall of Ships in that place, the tydes running counter, and one Ship may be in the tyde, and the other out, which may make great difference, and indeed lies more in the skill of the Pilot then in the Ship, in obſerving the ſetting of the tides, and conſequently to take the advantage of it; by which your Honours may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> will undertake to tell your Honours, that which he underſtands not. And for his propoſition to the Lords to build thoſe Frigates by the great, their Honours utterly refuſed it, knowing it a diſhonour to the Parliament to build Ships out of his Majeſties yard, having the beſt Ship-wrights in the Kingdome to perform that ſervice; and one, who had given ſuch teſtimony of his Art and skill in building of a Frigate, for the right Honourable the Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> that a better Saylor is not in <hi>England,</hi> nor <hi>Dunkirk:</hi> but the Lords told Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> if he would build one to trie his skill, he ſhould have his Majeſties yard at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> to build in, with timber, plancks and materialls needfull; which Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> refuſed to do, and ſaith, it was a diſhonour caſt upon him, and for no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113650:7"/>other cauſe, but that he could not build one by the great, that ſo he might get two or three hundred pound by the Parliament: And if the other Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrights are diſcontended (as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith) becauſe they did not build them by the great (as we believe they are not) yet we marvell that Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſhould ſuggeſt, that M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Pet</hi> the builder, acts againſt his affection, or deſires, being the King and Parliaments ſervant; unleſſe he would bring the Parliament in diſlike with the Ship-wrights, and ſo to bring them under a Cloud, as he hath endeavoured to eclipſe the Trinity-houſe. And as for the ſubtile plot (as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> calls it) in cauſing Maſter <hi>Pet</hi> Junior, to build the great Frigate and Maſter <hi>Pet</hi> ſenior to build the two leſſer; it is falſe and untrue, for Maſter <hi>Pet</hi> Junior, builds one of the ſmall ones, and Maſter <hi>Pet</hi> ſenior, builds the other ſmall one; and this we did to the end they might uſe the utmoſt of their skill to try who could build the beſt Saylor. And becauſe we had experience of the good performance of Maſter <hi>Pet</hi> ſenior, in building the <hi>Conſtant Warwick,</hi> he was appointed to build the great Frigate likewiſe: By all which your Honours may perceive, how he hath falſly traduced the Commiſſioners of the Navie, the Maſter, Wardens, and Aſſiſtants of the Trinitie-houſe; the principall men of the Corporation of the Ship-wrights; and all he drives at, is by his unjuſt aſperſions to bring the Parliament and them at ods, that ſo he might accompliſh his own ends. And thus we hope, we have given your Honours ſatisfaction in the building of the Frigates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, being the moneth of May, he ſtill ſings his old tune, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſing</hi> Englands <hi>Navie, which</hi> Maſter <hi>Burrell would have as weak as his brain; and tells ſtrange Stories of the mungrell</hi> Dunkirk, <hi>the contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Iriſh, <hi>and the inſulting</hi> Dutch, <hi>that they will not honour the Parliaments Ships nor acknowledge them Maſter of the Seas: And then by way of Inference, brings in his Maieſties horſes as fat as himſelf; how they were tired being led down to</hi> Barwick <hi>with empty ſaddles, and then compares the dead with the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, in theſe words; As theſe Royall horſes were clogged with too much fleſh, even ſo the Royall Navie is clogged with too many men; too much victuals, too many pieces of Ordnance, to much timber, and too much plank; and then ads further to make the Royall Navy more contemptible, he ſaith, the Ship-wrights were commanded to make the Ships now in the Navy, Ships for ſhaw, as well as for ſervice, and to carry many pieces of Ordnance never to be uſed, but at Feaſts, Salutations, and Landings. The example (ſaith Maſter</hi> Burrell) <hi>is lively in the</hi> Royall-Soveraign, <hi>an admirable Ship for coſtly Buildings, and coſt in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and which ads to the miracle, the Royall Ship (ſaith he) is never to be uſed for the Kingdoms good; And that the Navy for ſwift ſayling in Queen</hi> Eliſabeths <hi>dayes, was famous, and farre exceeding thoſe times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which we anſwer; As for the honour of the Narrow-Seas, it hath been kept in as much honour and reputation as ever; witneſſe the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> who hath commanded all Ships, where
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113650:7"/>ever his Honour came, to render due obedience: and Captain <hi>Owen</hi> in the <hi>Guardland,</hi> commanding a Squadron of foure or five Ships under the right Honourable Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> was ſent out by his Lordſhip to ſeek out the Kings Men of Warre. and all other that tranſported Armes or Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to his Majeſties Quarters, and being in the Channell, came in amongſt ſixtie ſail of <hi>Hollanders,</hi> whereof five or ſix Men of Warre; and did not onely make them all ſtrike, but ſent Captain <hi>Gilſon</hi> in the <hi>Warwick</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, who took out of the midſt of the Fleet the <hi>Tiger</hi> of <hi>Roterdam,</hi> and brought her away in deſpight of all thoſe Men of Warre, and ſent her to <hi>London:</hi> The next was Captain <hi>Batten,</hi> who being alone in the <hi>Conſtant-Reformation</hi> off of <hi>Beachy,</hi> met with the <hi>Vice-Admirall</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> and foure great Ships more; and although they ſuffered him to ſhoot divers ſhot at them, before they would ſtrike, yet when they ſaw his reſolution, they lowered their top-ſails, and did homage. Captain <hi>Ellis</hi> in the <hi>Providence,</hi> and Captain <hi>Thomas</hi> in the <hi>Warwick</hi> Frigate, commanded <hi>White</hi> the <hi>Vice-Admirall,</hi> and three more, to ſtrike in <hi>Torbay,</hi> which they did accordingly, though with ſome ſhot before they did their duty. And for the Royall horſes being tired in being led down to <hi>Barwick,</hi> it is not ſo with the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Ships, for they are never weary with ſailing: And for too many Men, Ordnance and victuals, we know other Princes Ships that carry more, and yet not of their burthen: And as for Timber and Plank, we ſhall refer that to the judgement of the beſt Sea-men, and Ship-wrights in the Kingdome. But we wonder much at the impudence of this Gent. who dare fay, the Royall Ships of the Navie were built for ſhow, and carry many pieces of Ordnance never to be uſed, but at Feaſts, Salutations, and Landings; when there is not one piece of Ordnance in any Ship of the Navie, but is both uſefull and ſerviceable for a defenſive and offenfive Warre: And to bring the Navie into a more contemptible condition, he makes the <hi>Royall-Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</hi> (the beſt Man of Warre in Chriſtendome) to be incapable of doing ſervice for the Kingdomes good. When Captain <hi>Rainsborow,</hi> whom Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Burrell</hi> confeſſeth in his time, was the moſt eminent Commander in this Kingdom, had the triall of her in the channell of <hi>England,</hi> and at his return reported to his Majeſtie, that he never ſet his foot in a better conditioned Ship in all his life, And as for her Force, ſhe is not inferiour to the greateſt Ship in Chriſtendome. And for the Ships in Queen <hi>Eliſabeths</hi> dayes, ſo famous for Sailing; this Kingdom was never better furniſhed with good Saylors and Ships for defence, then at this preſent, farre exceeding thoſe times. By theſe and the precedent Articles, your Honours may perceive how under a ſpecious ſhow of a well-affected man to the State, he covertly by his Calumnies, ſeeks to bring the Navie into a contemptible Condition; not onely in the opinion of this Nation, but alſo of Strangers; that ſo they may be incouraged to attempt that, which they never hitherto durſt put in practice.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113650:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>In the next place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>propounds how the Royall Navie with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle charge, may be reduced into a ſerviceable poſtare, and into ſuch a Warlike po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, as will inable the Parliament to recover and maintain the Soveraigntie of the Seas, as in the Raign of Queen</hi> Eliſabeth <hi>of happy memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is ſtrange that Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſhould know more, then all the Ship-wrights in the Kingdom being a man that many years hath had no practice, and conſequently leſſe experience. And as for the little charge in reducing the Navie, the coſt that will be ſpent in cutting down one of the firſt and ſecond Rate-Ships and finiſhing them, will build the hull of a ſhip of the fourth Rate that ſhall carry thirty pieces of Ordnance, that will do more ſervice then they will do when they are cut down to one Tire of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; for the reaſons given in our firſt Article. And as for the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of the Seas, it is true, that ſince theſe diſtracted times, the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> have been very inſolent in wearing their Flags, as they have formerly done: But ſuch hath been the valour and courage of our Commanders, that as often as they have been met withall, they have been compelled to do their dutie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In folio</hi> 9. <hi>Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith, that when the Royall Navie ſhall be reduced into a ſerviceable poſture, the Parliament may ſave a fourth part of that vaſt charge, which hath been ſpent at Sea, ſince theſe diſtracted times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which we anſwer, We do not know what Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> calls redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Navie, but we conceive it is rather a deſtruction of the Navie, to cut down the firſt, ſecond and third Rate-Ships, which are walls of Braſſe to defend this Kingdom: And as for ſaving a fourth part of the charge, that hath been ſpent at Sea ſince theſe diſtracted times, we are yet to learn; although we have conſtantly followed Marine affairs theſe thirty years, and upwards, how ever we deſire that Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> will give reaſons how the fourth part of the charge may be ſaved, and ſuch Fleets maintained at Sea, as have been ſet forth theſe foure yeares paſt, without dimunition of the ſtrength and glory of the Navie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We come now to Maſter</hi> Burrells <hi>laſt quere, where he deſires the Honourable Houſe of Commons to examine what the Kings party would have attempted, that they have not freely effected; have they not (ſaith he) been ſupplied from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas with Ordnance, Armes, and Ammunition, and imported and exported eminent Traytours? and have not both</hi> Iriſh, <hi>and</hi> Turks, <hi>landed in this Kingdom, and carried away Men, Women and Children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Although it be true that this quere belongs not wholly to us to anſwer our Office being no other then to act by the Parliament, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Lords and Commons of the Admiralties Order to equip, victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and Manne the Ships, deſtinated for the Guard of the Sea; as alſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their Lordſhips of the repair of Ships Docks and Houſes in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſeverall yards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We thought it our duty to give an anſwer in the juſt vindication of thoſe Noble Lords and Commons of the Committe of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113650:8"/>the Admiraltie, who ſit at the Helm; that there hath been as much care taken to prevent the landing of <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the tranſportation and importing of Traytors, The bringing in of Ammunition, as the wit of man could invent; and truly if <hi>Dunkirk</hi> being a ſmall Town, in one year took from the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> notwithſtanding the great Fleets they yearly ſet out, 80 Sail of Ships: how much more might the Kings men of Warre, being aſſiſted by the <hi>French, Hollanders,</hi> and <hi>Dunkirkers,</hi> who ſeemed to be the Parliaments friends, carry in Armes, Traitors and Ammunition, into the Kings Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? yet they paid dear for it; For although ſome eſcaped yet many were taken, witneſſe a States Man of Warre, going into <hi>Scarborough</hi> with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Armes; The King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Ship bound in for <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> laden with Armes, and divers <hi>French</hi> men, and <hi>Hollanders</hi> bound into <hi>Briſtoll, Falmouth, Dartmouth, Scarborough,</hi> and <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> with Armes and other proviſions, which the Collectors for Prize-goods can certifie, one and other, to the number of 110. Sail, beſides many Ships with his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. And as for the Turks landing in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> they landed in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Quarters and not in the Parliaments; and if Poſts and Intelligence might have gone along that Coaſt, they might have been prevented, the Parliament Ships being at the ſeige of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> in defending that Town, but never heard of it untill too late, and that from his Majeſties Quarters. And thus we hope, we have anſwered Maſter <hi>Burrells</hi> falſe aſperſions and calumnies, caſt upon the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons of the Admiralty, the Commiſſioners of the navie; the Maſter, Wardens, and Aſſiſtants of the Trinity-houſe, with the principall members of the corporation of Ship-wrights, and all for his own ends, to get into imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113650:9"/>
            <head>The ANSWER of the COMMISSIONERS of the NAVIE, to the Generall Charge, intituled ENGLANDS OUTGAURD, or ENGLANDS ROYALL NAVIE, ſurveyed and lamented by ANDREWES BURRELL Gentleman, ſometimes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in the Navie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſt place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith, that there is not one Ship in the Navie that hath taken any one of the Kings Men of War, ſince theſe Warres began; and that the greateſt Commanders which the Parliament hath ſent forth; as Admiralls, Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, and Rear-Admiralls, are ſo farre from ſubduing any of the Kings Men of Warre, that there is not any one of them that have ſhot one ſhot in anger, ſince theſe diſtracted Wars began, though many hundred thouſands of pounds have been ſpent in guarding the Seas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is falſe, and ſcandalous againſt that noble Lord, and worthy Gentlemen that have commanded the Parliament Ships; for we ſhall make it appear, that ſince theſe Wars began, the Parliament have taken and ſunk 39 Ships and Pinaces, Men of War, who had his Majeſties Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: the names of the Ships, with their Captains that took them, for better ſatisfaction, we have here under inſerted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viz.</hi> Captain Batten, in the Saint George, took the Bonaventure, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of Ireland; the Swallow, Vice-Admirall; and the Robert-Frigate: Captain Swanley, in the Leopard, took the Globe, Admirall of Briſtoll; the Providence, Vice-Admirall; Diſcovery, Rear-Admirall; and the <hi>Henrietta Pinnace Regis:</hi> Captain Smith, in the Swallow, took the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and Hart-Frigate: Captain Pecket, in the May-flower,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113650:9"/>took the Providence <hi>Regis:</hi> Captain Thomas, in the eighth Whelp, took the May-flower, Admirall of Falmouth, and chaſed on ſhore her Vice-Admirall and Rear-Admirall at Breſt; alſo he ſunk a Frigate of Sir Nicholas Criſpes: Captain Thomas, Captain Elliſon, and Captain Whitty, being all in company, took one Man of War: Captain Elliſon, in the Providence, ſunk a Man of War of Foy, and alſo the Fortune of Dunkirk: Captain Stansby, in the Providence, and Captain Rew, in the Robert, took Brown Buſhell's Frigate, called the Cavendiſh: Captain Pet, in the Mari-roſe, took the Roebuck-Frigate of Dunkirk: Captain Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin, in the Grey-hound, took the Conſtant, Captain Skinner Commander of her: Captain Clark, in the Joſline, took the Swan-Frigate, &amp;c. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Haddock, in the John, took a States Man of War laden with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Regis:</hi> going to Scarborough; and alſo the Salvator: Captain Beddall, in the Hector, took the Black-horſe, and Captain, Denton's Ship, and two Men of War of Scarborough; and likewiſe an Oſtend Man of War, bound for Scarborough: Captain Gattensby, in the Proſperous, took a Daniſh Man of War laden with Arms: Captain Stansby, in the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, took the Jennet, a Dunkirk Man of War: Captain Gilſon, in the Conſtant Warwick, took the Royaliſt: Captain Cox, in the Royaliſt, took a Dogger-Boat of four Guns: Captain Pilgrim, in the Sampſon, took a Dogger-Boat: The Iriſh Squadron, took the Welcome-Pink, Encreaſe: Tryall-Pink, Charles Trough, Peter-Frigate, and the William and John; Captain Wodward, in the Roebuck, took a Dunkirk-Frigate of Falmouth; which Frigate is now in the Service, as moſt of the reſt are.</p>
            <p>Beſides at leaſt 110 Merchant-Ships, trading in and out of thoſe Ports in defection to the Parliament with Ammunition. Money, and Goods, that have been taken and made Prize by the Parliament-Ships, to a large Sum; and many that have been reſtored to well-affected perſons; and divers that on the earneſt requeſt of the Spaniſh French, and Dutch Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, that have been delivered back unto them.</p>
            <p>By which it doth appear that ſome ſhot have been made in anger, and not onely at Sea but it is well known to the Parliament, that the Navie hath not had the leaſt ſhare in preſerving of Plymouth, the Iſle of Wight, Hampton. Portſmouth, Weymouth, Lyme, Hull, Wales, and Ireland, and divers other places which otherwiſe had been in the hands of the Kings Forces at this time: Neither muſt we omit the great ſervice done in the Downs, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1642, where, by the wiſdom and valour of the Right Honourable Robert Earl of Warwick, Admirall in the James, Captain William Batten, Vice-Admirall in the Saint George, and a mixture of Sea-men, Commanders of the beſt of his Majeſties Ships, then in the Downs; At which time there was a Meſſage ſent from his Majeſty, by the hands of Sir John Pennington and Maſter Villiers, directed to the Earl of Warwick, therein requiring the delivery up of the Fleet into the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113650:10"/>hands of Sir John Pennington, appointed by his Majeſty to be Admirall: This Meſſage being ſpred amongſt the Commanders and Sea-men in the Fleet, it invited the greater part of the Gentlemen, who commanded di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of thoſe Ships, then preſent, to ſubmit unto his Majeſties Meſſage, and to ſtand upon their guard, refuſing all commands, the Earl of Warwick laid upon them in obedience to the Parliament. The names of the Captains and Ships on either ſide, are hereafter expreſſed.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Commanders that ſubmitted to His MAjESTIES Meſſage.</head>
               <item>Sir John Mince, Rear-Admirall in the Victory.</item>
               <item>Captain Fog. in the Reformation.</item>
               <item>Captain Slingsby, in the Guard-land.</item>
               <item>Captain Burley, in the Anthelope.</item>
               <item>Captain Wake, in the Expedition.</item>
               <item>Captain Fox, in the Lyon.</item>
               <item>Captain Hill, in the tenth Whelp.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Commanders who continued in obedience to KING and PARLIAMENT.</head>
               <item>The Right Honourable Robert Earl of Warwick, Admirall in the James.</item>
               <item>Captain Batten, Vice-Admirall in the Saint George.</item>
               <item>Captain Thomas Trenchfield, in the Vnicorn.</item>
               <item>Captain George Hatch, in the Mary.</item>
               <item>Captain Richard Swanley, — Charles.</item>
               <item>Captain Brian Harriſon, — Vauntguard.</item>
               <item>Captain Richard Owen, — Entrance.</item>
               <item>Captain Henry Bethell — Mari-roſe.</item>
               <item>Captain Martin, — Martin.</item>
               <item>Captain Thomas Aſhley — Sampſon.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But it pleaſed God, that by the integrity of the Sea-men (who faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſtood to that Noble Lord,) the Commanders of ſuch Ships that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the Parliament, were quickly ſuppreſſed and reduced to his Lordſhips obedience, who placed other Captains in their room: which was a very great Service; and indeed (under God) the protection of the Parliament and Kingdom: for had his Majeſty been poſſeſſed of that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113650:10"/>Fleet, he would thereby have been Maſter of the Seas, and blockt up the City of London in their Relief and Trade: By which all men may ſee, that the many hundred thouſands of pounds, which (Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith) hath been ſpent, is not waſted in vain, as he maliciouſly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſecond place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith; The Officers of the Navie have been adviſed how they may make part of the Navie able to ſubdue the Kings Men of War, with the ſaving of one</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h <hi>part of that vaſt charge which hath been ſpent at Sea: but in oppoſition to any good advice, they will not be moved to reduce one of the old Ships for a triall; and though the Kingdom periſh, they will perſiſt in deluding the State, commending and ſupporting the Title of a Royall Navie, when in truth it is unſerviceable, I beleeve I may ſafely ſay, contemptible, in the eſteem of Strangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We cannot but wonder at the imbecillity of this man, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the opinion of the ableſt Sea-men and Ship-wrights of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, would cut down the beſt Ships in the Navie, and make them nimble Frigates; as if the three Frigates now building, and near twenty more now in the Service, were not (by Gods aſſiſtance) able to ſubdue half a dozen which are left untaken of his Majeſties Men of War, and the moſt of them of ſo ſmall force, that they are not conſiderable, if any of the Parliaments Frigates meet with them. And for ſaving of one 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part of the charge, we beleeve, if he bring the Navie into ſuch a poſture as he pretends, from Ships to Frigates, he may very well ſave one 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part of the charge, both in men, Victuals, and Ordnance: But we deſire to know of this Dull Carpenter, how he will do this without diſabling the Navie: And for ſupporting the Title of a Rovall Navie, we dare preſume to aver and maintain, and that in deſpite of Malignants, and all Enemies to the King and Parliament, That no Prince in Chriſtendom hath ſo many brave Ships for a defenſive and offenſive War, as the Kingdom of England hath at this preſent; having of the firſt rank 4 Ships, that carry from 50 to 80 peeces of Ordnance, 12 Ships of the ſecond rank that carry from 44 to 50 peeces of Ordnance, 9 Ships of the third rank that carry from 36 to 44 peeces of Ordnance, and of the fourth rate, 3 Ships which carry from 24 to 32, 2 Ships of the fifth rate carrying from 16 to 20 peeces of Ordnance, 3 of the ſixth rate carrying from 10 to 16 peeces of Ordnance, beſides 20 Ships and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats which the Parliament hath bought and taken. And if theſe Ships ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear contemptible in the eyes of Strangers, we ſhall refer it to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any moderate man: As alſo whether it be fit, that Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> ſhould publiſh to all Strangers, That the Navie of this Kingdom is in an unſerviceable condition; when it doth appear to all men, that it was never better managed, nor in a better poſture, then now it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith; The Officers of the Navie do know that the Navie hath not performed any good Service for the Kingdom, ſince
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113650:11"/>theſe diſtracted Wars began; yet ſuch is their plotting, that they will continue it in an unſerviceable condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Officers of the Navie do know, that the Navie hath performed many good Services for the Kingdom, as it is ſet forth in our Anſwer to the firſt Article: And our plotting hath never been otherwiſe, then for upholding and maintaining the honour of the Navie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the fourth place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith; That the Officers of the Navie being thus reſolved to accompliſh their own ends, they ſuffer the Royall Navie to lie rotting at</hi> Chatham <hi>and</hi> Portſmouth, <hi>at a dear rate, a rate that exceeds all former Preſidents; and that they hire the worſt of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Ships and Colliers, to ſerve in their room: and that he is hold to ſay, they are more ſluggiſh then any Ships in the Navie; and ſome of thoſe Ships are belonging to the Officers of the Navie, and ſome to Parliament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which we Anſwer, That it is falſe; for the Ships of the Navie were never better repaired, upheld, and maintained, then ſince they were in the hands of the Parliament, as by our particular Anſwer hereafter ſhall appear: And as for their lying in Harbour, and Merchant-Ships take up to ſerve in their room, it will appear that there hath been yearly employed at Sea, as many of the Ships of the Navie, as was held in the wiſedom of the Parliament fit, for the number of men aſſigned for the yearly guard of the three Kingdoms: which men, had they been employed in the Ships of the Navie, moſt of them being great Ships, would have contracted a vaſt charge, and not have ſpread ſufficiently to guard the three Kingdoms: For example; There hath been employed yearly from 60 to 70 Sails; <hi>viz,</hi> upon the Coaſt of Ireland and Lancaſhire, 25 Ships; for the guard of Severn and Wales, 5; for the guard of the Channell of England, 15 Ships; for the guard of Guernſey, and thoſe Iſlands, 3; for the Downs to attend Convoys, 8; and for the guarding of the North Coaſt, and Kingdom of Scotland, 12 Ships. By which it will appear, there is a neceſſity of hiring Merchant-Ships, in regard the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie conſiſted but of 32 Ships when we came in Office; and the hiring of Merchant-Ships is no other then what hath been uſuall in all times of War, time out of mind: And if the whole Navie ſhould be year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employed; beſides the vaſt charge it would contract, it would be too great an adventure for the Kingdom to undergo: for if the Fleet ſhould by caſualty of Weather, or by accident of War, miſcarry, there would be no reſerve left to make another Fleet, and ſo the whole Kingdom ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to danger; whereas if ſix or eight of the greateſt Ships be left in Harbour, with the aſſiſtance of thirty or fourty of the Merchant-Ships, (which may be alwayes had in the River of Thames,) they will make a ſufficient Fleet to encounter any Force that ſhall come againſt them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113650:11"/>the Merchant-Ships do coſt the Kingdom nothing near the charge that the great Ships of the Navie ſtand in; and yet they run the adventure of their Ships; Ordnance, and Ammunition: If in caſe the great Ships of the Navie be employed in the room of Merchants, the State bears the adventure, which in caſe of loſſe of a ſecond Rate-Ship, will amount to 25000 pounds. We ſay not this to diſcourage the Parliament from building of more nimble Frigates, which may leſſen the hiring of Merchant-Ships, if there ſhould be the like occaſion; but to let your Honours know, there hath been nothing loſt in taking up Merchant-Ships, in the room of the great Ships of the Navie. And further, if all the Navie ſhould be conſtantly employed yearly at Sea, they would be ſo out of repair in two or three years, that the Sea would be left unguar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by them, and ſo be forced to hire all Merchant-Ships. And as for ſuch Ships Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith belong to Parliament-men, and the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Navie; we refer you to our Anſwer to Maſter <hi>Burrells</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In his fifth Article, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>affirmeth, That thoſe Captains that have been moſt valiant, have been diſcouraged; and thoſe that have deſerved puniſhment, preferred to places of truſt; and in particular, Captain Man, with others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In Anſwer to this charge; becauſe we will not reiterate things twice, as in ſome things we are forced to do, in regard of Maſter <hi>Burrells</hi> wandring progreſſe; we ſhall herein refer our ſelves to his particular charge, wherein we doubt not but to give your Honours ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, he makes a long diſcourſe of Services done by Captain Man and Captain Gilſon, in two nimble Frigates, againſt Mucknell in a great Ship; and makes his inference, That if two nimble Frigates can deſtroy ſo great a Ship as Mucknells, with</hi> 42 <hi>peeces of Ordnance, there is no Ship in the World able to encounter a Ship of the ſecond rank, being fortified with</hi> 20 <hi>Demi-canon, every ſhot weighing</hi> 32 <hi>pounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For Anſwer thereunto: It is falſe that thoſe 2 Frigates, although accompanied with another good Ship of 20 peeces of Ordnance, all three having 62 Guns, and manned with 280 men, yet did deſtroy Mucknells Ship, ſhe not being of the force of a third rate Ship in the Navie; But rather foiled them all, and forced them to leave her; by which means, the next day, ſhe went for Silly, where in going in (for want of a good Pilot) ſhe was caſt away: Whereby it doth appear, that Maſter Burrells Obſervation is grounded upon a falſe Principle; For if a Merchant-Ship was able to defend her ſelf from three Frigates, armed with whole Culverin and Demi-culverin, and not with ſmall Ordnance, (as Maſter Burrell ſaith,) much more might ſhe have done againſt one Ship with one Tire of Ordnance: But on the contrary, had one of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113650:12"/>Majeſties Ships, of the ſecond or third rank, come up with Mucknell, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, as now they are, with two Tire of Ordnance; doubtleſſe Muck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell muſt have ſubmitted: And we do beleeve, That if any ſuch Ship had been in view of Mucknell, ſhe would have ſailed as well as Mucknell's Ship, and not been liable to that foule aſperſion of being ſluggiſh, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Maſter Burrell brands them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith, There is a want in the Fleet, of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, Pole-axes, Swords, and Fire-works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which we Anſwer; It is not the duty of our Places to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh any Ammunition, but belongeth to the Officers of the Ordnance: yet we do verily beleeve, that for all ſuch Arms as are uſefull for ſervice, are by them ſupplied; the rather for that we have heard no complaint from any Commander employed in any of the Kings Ships: but as for ſuch Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Ships as are taken up by us, they are furniſhed with Piſtols, Swords, Pikes, and all other Arms for War, fitting for defence and offence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In his eighth Article, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>reciteth the new Frigates, and would lay an asperſion on the Officers of the Navie, That they ſhould give to the Maſter Ship-wrights Directions in the building of them; and that when they were built, they would not be ſo ſerviceable as they ſhould be, the work being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed before it be begun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſets down in this Article, is falſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, we having already ſet forth, by whoſe Directions theſe Frigates were built: and if they prove unſerviceable, (as we beleeve the contrary,) yet they cannot be ſo bad as the Mari-roſe, built by Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> being the moſt ſluggiſh Ship in the Navie; which we have lately had in the Dock, and cauſed to be lengthened Aft, with other works done unto her, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make her a ſerviceable Ship. And as for the work being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed before it be begun, that ſeems to us a Paradox, and carrieth no more truth with it then what elſe he hath ſet forth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In his ninth Article, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>begins to tell his old Story with a piece of Non-ſence, in theſe words: Vnleſſe the Parliament do thus at an exceſsive charge, ſend many great ſluggiſh Ships to Sea, the honour of the Sea is loſt, and ſo loſt, that it cannot be regained; and yet in a contradiction ſalves up the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſaith; But by reducing the Navie into a ſerviceable poſture for theſe times, into a nimble condition, with one Tire of Ordnance and no more, and ſome Drakes for cloſe Fights, with this caution; the greater the Ship is, the greater the Ordnance, and number of men, as the Ship can well accommodate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> By the firſt part of Maſter <hi>Burrellls</hi> Non-ſence, he would have ſluggiſh Ships ſent to Sea, or elſe the honour of the Sea is loſt, but at laſt ſaith, That the Navie muſt be reduced into a ſerviceable poſture for theſe times; as if the Navie were to be altered upon every turn of the Tide; and in ſtead of having the Navie maintained for the ſtrength of the Kingdom
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113650:12"/>againſt all forraign Forces that ſhould invade the Realm, he would bring them to one Tire of Ordnance, pretending to ſuppreſſe the Kings Men of War, which are no other then ſmall Frigates, Dogger-Boats Sloops, and the like: and then indeed he would make Englands Navie contemptible, both at home and abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then he layes down what manner of Ordnance he would have put into the firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth Rate-Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For Anſwer thereunto: This Gentleman it ſeems would go about to teach Minerva, to inſtruct others, that know better then himſelf: And whereas he would have none but whole Canon, Demi-canon, whole Culverin and Demi-culverin, according to their ſeverall ranks; we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Ordnance of his Majeſties Ships are already ſo well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and with ſuch good advice, that there needs none or Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relis</hi> Reformation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place he ſaith, The common Sea-men are ſo groſly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zened of their thirds of Prize-goods, that many thouſands have left the Kingdom; and thoſe that remain, ſo dis-heartened, that no good Service can be expected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> Although this charge concerns not us, yet to our knowledge it is moſt falſe, as the Collectors for Prize-Goods will make it appear, when they ſhall be thereunto called. And for the many thouſands of Sea-men that have left the Kingdom; this is as true as the reſt: for we could never learn of any that deſerted the Parliament, but ſuch as have alwayes lived as Pirats and Robbers at Sea formerly; the Kingdom being better without ſuch than to have them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Gentlemans Concluſion is, That Ship that doth not ſail well, cannot ſerve well; and that man that denieth this truth, and cannot ſhew a better remedy for a Reformation of the Navie, that man is wilfully ignorant, or a Traitor to the State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> In this particular we ſhall be brief, and conclude; He that ſets forth falſhoods and endevoureth to deſtroy the Navie, (being the Walls of the Kingdom,) and produceth no better reaſons, is either groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or an Enemy to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And thus we have gone through Maſter <hi>Burrells</hi> falſe ſuggeſtions, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous informations and notorious falſhoods; and for the Vindication of our integrity, we humbly ſubmit to the Juſtice of the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113650:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113650:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113650:14"/>
            <head>The Anſwer of the COMMISSIONERS of the Navie, to the Particular Charge of Maſter ANDREWES BURRELL, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted out of his Generall Charge.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter</hi> Burrell <hi>in his firſt Charge, ſaith, That divers of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Ships have been ſuffered to lie rotting in Harbour; as alſo foure of his Majeſties Ships were lately condemned to be ſold; yet ſuch is the providence of the Officers of the Navie, that thoſe rotten Ships are ſtill continued, and do coſt the Common-wealth,</hi> 1500. l. per annum, <hi>to keep them above water; and that by two other Ships, the State may ſave</hi> 1800. l. per annum, <hi>and neither weaken, nor diſhonour the Navie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To which we anſwer, That it is falſe, and ſcandalous; for we ſhall make it plainly appear, That not onely thoſe ſhips mentioned by him but the whole Navie is in a farre better condition, then when his Majeſty left the Parliament. And firſt for the <hi>Soveraign;</hi> ſhe was carved, graved, and trimmed, both under water, and above water, and made fit for the Kingdoms ſervice, the laſt Summer. And that ſince his Majeſties ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; there have been repaired in drie Dock, the Saint <hi>Andrew, Victory, Charles, Vnicorn, Vantguard, Conſtant, Convertine, Guard-land Bonaventure, Anthelope, Swallow, Mari-roſe,</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> Frigate, beſides the <hi>Triumph, Providence</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Dock; which Ships when his Majeſtie left them, were all defective, and moſt of them unſerviceable. And as for the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuch, Aſſerance,</hi> Saint <hi>Dennis,</hi> and <hi>Adventure,</hi> they were caſt three years or more, before his Majeſties departure from the Parliament; yet his Majeſty would never ſuffer them to be ſold, untill new Ships were built in their rooms. But the Parliament, at one inſtance, being informed of the yearly charge of thoſe Ships, gave Order in October laſt, to put them to ſale; which was done accordingly, but in regard the Winter was come, and the charge would be great to the buyer to bring them up to <hi>London,</hi> no man offered a penny for them; but now the time of year is come, and three new Frigates upon the ſtocks, and ſhortly to be lanched, we have put them to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113650:14"/>ſail. And for what other Ships, not herein mentioned, they are trimmed every year; and kept as well, as ever they were, ſince the Kingdom ſtood. And as for the two other Ships which Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> mentions in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, in which 1800. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> may be ſaved, and neither weaken nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Navie; we confeſſe, That is a good ſervice, if Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> can make it good, and we deſire the Honourable Houſes, that he may give rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons how it may be done, without weakening the Guard of the Navie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, he ſaith, That the</hi> May-flower <hi>is an old Ship, and hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been a Collier, and deſires to know how many Men of Warre ſhe hath taken for the</hi> 18000. l. <hi>ſhe hath received of the State. And that the</hi> John <hi>is an old ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh Ship, and hath not taken one Prize, nor that her company have hopes to take any hereafter. And that the</hi> Nicholas <hi>is a very ſluggiſh Ship; by which be would inferre, that the Parliament imployed none, but ſluggiſh Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Concerning theſe worſt of Merchants Ships, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> is pleaſed to call them, the May-flower, John, and Nicholas: As for the May-flower, ſhe hath been ever held a good ſailer as moſt in the River, and of good force, inſomuch, that ſhe fetcht up, and fought with three Dunkirk Frigates in Seavern; and had taken them, if an unfortunate ſhot had not killed the Captain, by name Captain Cock: Beſides many good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices done by her upon the coaſt of Ireland, both in the relief of Youghall, and taking Dingley Couch; ſhe likewiſe took the Providence-<hi>Regis,</hi> in Humber, and after beat the enemy from a Fort upon Humber, and took their Ordnance. And as for the John, ſhe is no Merchants Ship, but belongs to the State; yet when Captain Haddock was in her, ſhe tooke a States Man of War, which was laden with Powder, Arms, and Merchants goods bound into Scarborough; which Powder and Arms were of great uſe to the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Army, when they came firſt into Sunderland; with other Ships laden with Iron, Deals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which were made uſe of by the ſaid Army. And after Captain Zachary came into her, under God, the ſaid Ship and her company had not the leaſt ſhare in taking in of Scarborough, in keeping the enemy from water, as alſo all relief by Sea, although attempted by the Kings Men of War; and in a skirmiſh on ſhore, the Captain loſt his life. And as for the Nicholas ſince ſhe hath been in Ireland, ſhe hath done as good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice as any Ship whatſoever; although Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> brand her, yet Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Crowther the Vice-Admirall in his letter to us, deſired that ſhe might be continued in the laſt winters ſervice, being an active Ship. And as for the 18000l. received for the May-flower, we think it is far ſhort of that ſumme. Yet when victualls, wages, wear and tear, are deducted, there will no great matter remain for the Adventure, which remains yet unpaid, and due from the State; as likewiſe to all other Merchant Ships that are in the ſervice; by reaſon of which we had much adoe to get a competent number of Ships, to ſerve for this Summers expedition. By which your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours may perceive how Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſeeks to diſgrace the Merchants
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113650:15"/>Ships, as he hath done the Royall Navie: yea thoſe Merchants Ships that have done the Parliament beſt ſervice, as in his next Article will appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the third place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>begins to racke his memory, and complains of divers other good Ships, and ſaith, they are Colliers, and calls them the worſt of Ships; as the</hi> Hector, <hi>the</hi> Dragon, <hi>the</hi> Green-Dragon, <hi>the</hi> Hopefull Luke, <hi>and the</hi> Exchange. <hi>And that there were ſeven</hi> Dunkirk <hi>Frigates, offered to be ſold to the Officers of the Navie, for leſſe then</hi> 5000 l. <hi>But the Officers of the Navie refuſed them, and thought it better thrift to beſtow</hi> 11000 l. <hi>upon three Frigates, and that when they arebuilt, (if they be built according to the directions given by the Officers of the Navie to the Maſter-Ship-wrights) he believes (as he doth all things elſe) that they will not be ſerviceable, as thoſe of</hi> Dunkirk <hi>and (ſaith he) thoſe</hi> Dunkirk <hi>Frigates ſo offered to this State, being encouraged by the King, and manned with diſcontented Sea-men for want of their thirds; have taken many Ships and goods from the Merchants of</hi> London, <hi>to an ineſtimable value.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the third Article, concerning the taking up of Colliers, which Maſter <hi>Bur ell</hi> calls the worſt of ſhips: And firſt for the Hector, Captain Beddall, ſhe hath done very good ſervice; firſt in taking a Ketch laden with Butter and Coals which came out of Newcaſtle which veſſell ſhe fetcht up in foure houres chaſe, meerly by ſailing; the next he took was Galliot Hoy, which came out of Newcaſtle with three thouſand and odde pounds in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to buy Armes, as likewiſe letters of credit for three thouſand more, the reſt Coals and Grindſtones; in five houres chaſe ſhe fetcht her up, notwithſtanding, ſhe was a choice veſſell for ſailing, taken up for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and Captain Cork, Treaſurer to the Earle of Newcaſtle, (who was imployed to buy the Armes) was in her, and brought priſoner to Dover. The next ſhe took, was a Kings Man of Warre, called the Black-horſe, which he chaſed a ſhore, and after took her, and brought her to London: thenext he chaſed Captain <hi>Denton</hi> a <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Man of War a ſhore, which was then caſt away; and after chaſed another Man of Warre, with divers proviſions bound for <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> which he chaſed till he had ſpent, his maſt; and after took him, and carried him into <hi>Burlington;</hi> the next was a Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, conveyed by Brown Buſhell, which he took, and ſent into Hull. Since that, he reſcued two North-Seamen, out of the hands of a <hi>Scarborough</hi> Man of Warre, with diverſe other good ſervices which did conduce to the benefit and honour of the Parliament, which the ſaid Captain Beddall can give a more particular Accompt of; and this is one of the Ships M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Burrell</hi> calls a Collier, and the worſt of Ships. This Ship hath been victualled, and manned by the State; and hath taken more prizes, then foure times her fraight amounts unto, the Ships Hull hired for 62 l. <hi>per menſem:</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed theſe Ships (although by Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> called Colliers) yet by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their great force, and ſmall draught of water, are the moſt fit Ships for that Coaſt, except Frigates, eſpecially in Winter time. As for the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> and <hi>Green-Dragon,</hi> they were taken up by the Committee for <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113650:15"/>to carry Souldiers to <hi>Holy-Iſland:</hi> and afterwards in regard of their good ſervice there, and at <hi>Barwick,</hi> they were taken up by Order of the Honourable Committee of the Navie, to guard the Northern Coaſt where they afterwards performed very good ſervice, in ſo much that Captain <hi>Greens</hi> Ship called the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> (which Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> calls the worſt of Ships) took divers Prizes and being in fight with one, the Captain was ſlain, and yet the Prize was taken. The <hi>Hopefull-Luke</hi> was a Merchant Ship, and no Collier, and the firſt voyage that ever ſhe made: And the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change was never imployed in the ſervice of the State. And as for the ſeven Frigats ſo mentioned in his charge, we heard of it upon the Exchange, and did acquaint the Honourable Committee of the Navie therewith; and although money (at that time) was ſo ſcarce, that the Committee could hardly find money to pay Marriners wages, and ſet forth our Fleet; yet notwithſtanding, they bought the <hi>Warwick, Cignet, Starre, Hind, Lilly,</hi> and <hi>Creſcent</hi> Frigates, which are now in the ſervice. By this your Honours may perceive how farre we have been from oppoſing the buying or building of Frigates, but have rather endeavoured to increaſe the number of them, being now at leaſt twenty. And whereas Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith, they might have been bought for five thouſand pound: he doth not tell your Honours, That they would coſt to be ſet to Sea, double the firſt coſt, as by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we have found in the aforeſaid Frigates. And whereas he chargeth us with giving directions to the Ship-wrights, for the building of three new Frigates, it is falſe; for the maſter Ship-wrights, with the Aſſiſtants of the Maſter of their Hall and the Maſter Carpenter of the <hi>Eaſt-India,</hi> Company, gave us under their hands, the dimenſions and ſcantlings by which the ſaid Frigates ſhould be built; and we doubt not, but they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their duty, one of theſe Frigates will be more ſerviceable, then three of thoſe mentioned by maſter <hi>Burrell.</hi> And as for the diſcontented Sea-men, where with the King hath manned his Ships, we are ſure they had no cauſe to be diſcontented, neither with the Parliament nor us; for the Honourable Houſes of Parliament, have been pleaſed to augment their wages foure ſhillings in a moneth. and give them the one third of all they took, which to moderate men ſhould have been an engagement: but in regard we are not of one mind, as well by ſea, as by land, and ſome had rather live Pyrates, then in an honeſt calling, there may be ſome Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh (although not thouſands) out of their ill affection to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that have deſerted the Cauſe, and yet in the Kings Men of Warre, there are three ſtrangers for one Engliſh man. And as for the Merchant Ships that have been taken, ſome have been ſurpriſed in going from their Convoy. And if <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> being a ſmall fiſher-town, taketh from the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> every year at leaſt eightie, or a hundred ſail of ſhips, and ſome years more; notwithſtanding, their great Fleets, ſet out every year for ſuppreſſing of them; how much more may all thoſe Ports of <hi>Flanders,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113650:16"/>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> infeſt our Coaſts, and yet in all this time, they have not taken any conſiderable Ship of force.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the fourth place, He falls upon ſome Members of Parliament, to wit, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Vaſſall, <hi>and Maſter</hi> Bence, <hi>That they are owners of ſome ſlaggiſh Ships now in the ſervice; as if their Ships were not as well able to ſerve, as any other Ships in the Kingdom, and likewiſe would fain make all the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of the Navie, Owners of ſuch Ships as are unfit for the ſervice of the State; when indeed and in truth, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>careth not what Ships they have, ſo he may have their places. Then he ſaith, he hath a new complaint which he hath (worn thred-bare, and as falſe as the reſt) teſtified by wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, (and never a word true.) And that is, that the beſt of Prizes have been eſtranged from the Parliament, and poſſeſſed by the Officers of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and their aſſociates; And that thoſe Ships have taken many rich Prizes, and when they have taken them, the Officers of the Navie have paid them off with the Parliaments pay, not allowing thoſe that have been moſt valiant, one penny for their ſhares, when the Prizes taken, have been worth</hi> 11000 <hi>l. And when the Sea-men demanded their ſhares, one of the Officers threatned them with impriſonment: By which unkind uſage</hi> (<hi>ſaith Maſter</hi> Burrell) <hi>many thouſand common Sea-men have been occaſioned to leave the Kingdom, and to ſerve againſt the Parliament. Then Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>doth beſeech their Honours to give him leave to acquaint them. that there is a</hi> Daniſh <hi>Ship now in the River of Thames, and ſaith, it is ſaid, ſhe was taken from the</hi> Danes <hi>by authority of Parliament; but ſaith, he knowes not whether Prize or no: But this he knoweth for certain, that Ship is fitter for the Parliament, then for any Subject in the Kingdom: and whereſoever the myſtery lieth (ſaith wiſe Maſter</hi> Burrell) <hi>that Ship was worth foure times ſo much money, as ſhe was ſold for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Maſter <hi>Samuel Vaſſall</hi> doth owe part of the <hi>May-flower,</hi> which is a ſerviceable Merchant Ship, and hath been often imployed, both in the <hi>Straits,</hi> and in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> by diverſe Merchants in London, being fortified with twenty eight peeces of Ordnance, and three Decks, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver underſtood by us to be a Collier, or ſluggiſh, as afore is declared. Maſter <hi>Alexander Bence,</hi> oweth a ſixteenth part of the <hi>Bleſsing,</hi> being a fit Ship for a Man of Warre, as any Ship of her burthen, in the River of Thames, and no ſluggard, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> would have her. And as for the <hi>Angel,</hi> we know of no ſuch Ship in the ſervice. And whereas Captain <hi>Crandley,</hi> and Captan <hi>Morris,</hi> are ſaid to be owners of the <hi>Anne Percie,</hi> it is not true, although the Ship be without exception, fit to ſerve any Prince in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome And whereas maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith, that Captain <hi>Crandley,</hi> and Captain <hi>Tweedy</hi> owe part of the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Providence;</hi> it is true Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Crandley,</hi> owes part of the <hi>Providence,</hi> though not in the ſervice, as likewiſe the <hi>Honour</hi> lately burnt. But as for Captain <hi>Tweedie,</hi> to be owner of either of them, or of any other Ship in the ſervice, it is falſe and untrue; although both the ſaid Ships were, and are ſerviceable both for the State,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113650:16"/>and Merchants, as appeared by the <hi>Honour,</hi> which fought with ſix of the Kings beſt Men of Warre, off <hi>Holy-head</hi> in Wales, and beat them into <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoll,</hi> and yet not in the States ſervice. And whereas we are charged with ſeverall Prizes taken by the Parliaments Ships, eſtranged from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and poſſeſt by the Officers of the Navie, and their aſſociates, and paid with the Parliaments pay, and their chief Commanders <hi>Iriſh:</hi> We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, it is notoriouſly falſe and ſcandalous, as what elſe touching this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle; And we deſire your Honours would be pleaſed, that he not proving it, we may have vindication, and be repaired in our reputation, which to us is as dear as our lives. And as for the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Ship, we know of ſuch a Ship taken by Captain <hi>Batten,</hi> and after delivered by the Honourable Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, to the Merchants Adventurers, together with her goods brought from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> which was by them ſold, in ſatisfaction for their wrongs received from the King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> and whether ſold cheap or dear, it no way concerneth the State, nor us. By this your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours may perceive the malice of this filly ignorant man, that will inform your Honours with that, which he cannot in the one, nor dare not in the other, make good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>recites diverſe Captains, by name Captain</hi> Man, <hi>Captain</hi> El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſon, <hi>Captain</hi> Wills, <hi>Captain</hi> Wild, <hi>and Captain</hi> Wappell; <hi>which he ſaith have done very good ſervice, but never received any reward, or preferment; And would make the world believe they are as diſcontented as himſelf, inſomuch, that he ſaith they would leave the Kingdom; when to our knowledge three of them are now at Sea, in the ſervice of the Parliament in three good Ships; and are neither diſcontented, nor unrewarded, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Burrell <hi>would have them to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to the fifth Article touching Captain <hi>Man</hi> ſo much commended by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burrell</hi> for his valour, wherein he ſaith, he hath deſerved a gold chain for his ſervice againſt <hi>Mucknell;</hi> we confeſſe had he and his conſorts perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and taken <hi>Mucknell,</hi> they all had well deſerved a good reward, but leaving him to harbour himſelf in <hi>Silly</hi> (where he run his Ship upon a rock) we cannot conceive how he or they have deſerved a reward; yet for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, we ſuppoſe the Honourable Committee of the Admiralty hath well preferred him, from the command of a ſmall Frigate, to command one of the beſt third rank Ships in the Navy. As for the good ſervice of Captain <hi>Elliſon,</hi> we are well ſatisfied; but that he hath not received any ſhares, of what is due, we cannot believe; or that he ſhould make any ſuch complaint unto Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> and not rather unto thoſe, who would do him right. As for Captain <hi>Iohn Wills,</hi> we marvell he ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of all others; for to our knowledge, he is well ſatisfied in the Service, being Captain of a ſmall Ship, the Lucie, he left the ſaid Ship, and lived ever ſince on ſhore; and if he be ſuch a man, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſets down, that he was intended to leave the Kingdom, and to ſeek employment in other Countreys; truely he is not to be truſted by the Parliament: for ſatisfaction of which, it will be neceſſary to queſtion him before he takes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113650:17"/>the command of Captain Plunkets Ship, being appointed by her owners to be Commander of her, in the States Service. And as for Captain John Wild, he hath been employed in the Service; and what his deportment was, we leave to the relation of the Right Honourable the Earl of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick: but in his laſt employment, he was Captain of the Cignet-Frigate upon the North-Coaſt, where we were given to underſtand, that in that Service, he and Captain Wills in the Lucie, took 4 Ships in Lynne-Deeps, belonging to that Town, when the Earl of Mancheſter was before it: his Lordſhip having taken the Town, the owners of the ſaid Ships petitioned his Lordſhip, for reſtoring of the ſaid Ships and Goods; upon which his Lordſhip was pleaſed to grant them their Ships and Goods again, they pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Captains 400 pounds ſalvage, <hi>viz.</hi> 100 pounds amongſt them and their Marriners in money, and a bond of 300 pounds to pay to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains at a certain time; which we underſtand they have received, but ought (in our opinions) to be accountable unto the State, in lieu of the Ships and Goods which were Prizes: beſides they pillaged the ſaid Ships, as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to us from the owners: By all which it doth appear, he hath no cauſe to complain for his thirds: And if he be ſuch a man as Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> makes him to be (which we do not beleeve,) we leave it to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours grave Wiſdoms to conſider whether he be ſo fit a man as Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> makes him, being one of thoſe (as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> ſaith) that out of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content would leave the Kingdom. As for Captain Wappall, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſtarved his men upon the Coaſt of Ireland, inſomuch, that they brought away the Ship for want of Victuals, when Sir Charles Coote had moſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe him after the taking in of Slego, the buſineſſe being taken into examination before us; and this is another of Maſter <hi>Burrells</hi> men, that would leave the Land; which, if ſo, are not fit men to be truſted by the State. And as for Captain Hawkeridge, we doubt not but the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earl of Warwick knows him well; and queſtionleſſe, if his Lordſhip had ſound him ſo capable of employment, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, he had been preferred as other men. And as for his Giant Captain Hodges, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> calls him, he alwayes ſerved in a private Man of War; by which employment, he made ſo good uſe of his time, that he hath purchaſed a great Ship, with which he is gone for Venice, laden with Merchants Goods; and not out of any diſcontent, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> would have it but for his own advantage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſixth place; he ſaith, That divers perſons are employed in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Service, that have deſerved puniſhment; and in ſtead thereof; have been preferred to places of truſt; and nominates Captain Shaftoe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> Concerning Captain Shaftoe, we did receive information, that he releaſed (after he had taken) one Leyton; who afterwards (as is ſaid) went into New-caſtle: Captain Shaftoe, after his coming to Town, did acquit himſelf, by divers witneſſes, of that crime; and will be ready at all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113650:17"/>times (being now Commander of Holy-Iſland) to give the Honourable Houſes further ſatisfaction. As for his Bill for his Ships Pay mentioned by Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> to be branded by Maſter <hi>Holland,</hi> in regard of the crime above-ſaid; it is true, it was ſo done by him againſt our conſent, long after he had ſigned it; but in regard we could not lay any juſt charge to Captain Shaftoe, and the money belonging to the owners, and not to him, for the Service of the Ship; we could not in juſtice, but take off the brand of the Bill; Captain Shaftoe being a reſponſible man, to anſwer any thing that afterwards ſhould be laid to his charge: and to our knowledge, he is a man that hath been faithfull to the Parliament, having done ſpeciall Services in landing in Northumberland, by the command of Captain Edward Hall, with the Anthelopes men and his own, being about 150, and coming to Colonell Hagerſtons houſe, being very ſtrong, ſummoned it, and took part of the out-houſes, and after, the Colonell himſelf thinking to eſcape away, his horſe was ſhot under him, &amp; ſo taken as alſo his Son in the Houſe; where they found ſtore of cloth for Souldiers coats for the Colonells Regiment, which he was raiſing: the taking of the ſaid Colonell, and bringing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſome priſoners, was the break-neck of that Regiment; which was at that time an excellent piece of ſervice: In the next place, he moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately entred into the Port of Holy-Iſland, the Caſtle and Iſland being for the King; and having not above 100 men, he firſt took the Town and the Iſland, and afterwards ſummoned the Caſtle, and had it delivered to the uſe of the Parliament: for which good ſervice, the honourable Houſes made him Captain thereof, where he remains to this day. And as for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hollands</hi> forbearing 14 moneths to ſit in Commiſſion for this and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other abuſes, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> pretends; we humbly deſire, that Maſter <hi>Holland</hi> may be examined, what theſe abuſes were, and by whom commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that, if ſo, they may receive condign puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſeventh place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>chargeth Captain Peacock with treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able practices, and ſaith, That he took a Veſſell, whereof was Maſter, one Hixon, laden with Arms and Ordnance for his Majeſty, and when Captain Peacocks men would have gone on board to ſearch her, he denied them, and told the men ſhe was laden with Apples, bound for Scotland; and after private conference in the Cabine together, Peacock ſet Hixon at liberty, and Hixon went into New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle, while Peacock was in ſight of him, and there delivered divers pieces of Ordnance, and other Ammunition for the King: for which treachery, ſaith Maſter</hi> Burrell, <hi>Peacock did neither ſuffer puniſhment nor fine, although the Articles againſt him were exhibited to the Officers of the Navie, and proved againſt him; yet notwithſtanding the great complaint, Peacok is lately made a Captain of one of the Parliaments Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As for the charge given againſt Peacock, we found no juſt proof againſt him, referring him to his defence preſented to the honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Admiralty, by which we doubt not but he hath given full
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113650:18"/>ſatisfaction, before their Honours admitted him into the ſervice again, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now Captain of the Warwick-Frigate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place, Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>chargeth one Bramble with cowardize, and ſaith, he was to convoy William Hazard in the</hi> Gift of God, <hi>from Ireland, with fifteen Maſts for the Service of the Navie; and Bramble commanding one of the Parliaments Frigates fortified with ſixteen peeces of Ordnance, met with two of the Kings Men of War, and at the ſight of them (as Maſter</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell <hi>ſaith) ran from his charge, and left Hazard to the mercy of the Enemy, who carried him into Falmouth; for which cowardly Service, Bramble was put out of the ſaid Frigate, by the ſpace of a year; but of late preferred to be Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of one of the Parliaments Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Concerning Captain Bramble leaving of his Convoy, which came from Ireland, with fifteen maſts; It is true, that two Frigates chaſed his Convoy in the morning, at break of day; and ſhe being ſo far a ſtearn, could not recover her before the Men of War had poſſeſſion of her, (as we are informed:) and ſince that, he hath been Maſter of the Anthelope with Captain Hall; where he behaved himſelf ſo well, that the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hall recommended him to the owners of the Ark, a Merchant-Ship, whereof he is now Commander.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ninth and laſt Quere (as he ſaith) is of great concernment, and thinks it not fit the common Sea-men ſhould be acquainted with it; and further ſaith, he finds them ſo full of diſcontent, that if he ſhould give them any encouragement, he fears they would be offenſive to the Parliament, becauſe (as Maſter</hi> Burrell <hi>ſaith) they have been groſly cozened in their thirds of Prize-goods, taken by Captain Swanley and Captain Moltons Squadrons, worth a great value, but (he ſaith) obſcured by tranſaction. Then he falls again upon Reformation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the Navie into a ſerviceable poſture for theſe times, and ſuch a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as will enable the Parliament to recover the Soveraignty of the Seas: And the jeſt is, he will defend England it ſelf from being invaded by Turks and Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robbers; and ſaith, The honour of the Sea is loſt, and the money ſpent little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than caſt into the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Concerning the fear he hath of the common Sea-men, of their coming to clamour at the Parliament-door; we beleeve there are no ſuch men, except promoted by Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> and his Agents. And for the Prizes taken by Captain Swanley and Captain Moltons Squadrons, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to the Collectors for Prizes and Prize-goods, who can give a very good account thereof. As concerning the Gentlemans concluſions, of his mark and aim for reforming of the Navie into a ſerviceable poſture; We hope we have given a full ſatisfactory Anſwer to your Honours: But we wonder that he ſhould be ſo impudently bold, as to charge the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the expence of ſo much money to be ſpent at Sea, or rather caſt into the Sea; when it appeareth, that the Navie, under God, hath not had the leaſt ſhare in preſerving the Kingdom, for the reaſons given aforeſaid.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113650:18"/>And as for the honour of the Sea, we dare be bold to ſay, it hath never been better upheld, then ſince our Fleets have been abroad; where they have been, and ſtill are Maſters of the Seas, in the face of the Parliaments Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And as for the Reformation of the Navie ſo much mentioned by Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> we know not what he means, unleſſe it be to deſtroy it, if it be no other than what by him is ſet forth; and in former times would have been held treaſon, in any Projector that ſhould have endevoured to put the ſame in practice. And we much wonder, that he, or any man, dares preſume to inform the Parliament, to bring Englands Royall Navie into ſuch a contemptible and weak condition, as this Gentleman would do by his Reformation, contrary to the opinion of the moſt skilfull Sea-men and Ship-wrights of the Kingdom: And therefore we could wiſh, that Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> ſo much inſiſting upon a Reformation of the Navie, would firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf of ſuch groſſe ignorance of which he now ſtands guilty. And thus we hope we have anſwered both his Generall and Particular Charge, referring both it and our ſelves to the grave Wiſedom of the honourable Houſes of Parliament, from whom we hope to have vindication, and repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for thoſe many unjuſt aſperſions and falſe accuſations againſt our perſons and reputation, ſet forth by Maſter <hi>Burrell,</hi> in his Pamphlet.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THen he writes his Poſtſcript, and ſhews of what rank the Ships ſhall be, which he intends to reform; and then he ſaith, If the State had ten times as many Pinaces, and ten times ſo many Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates as are now employed, the honour of the Sea cannot be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by them: It is the Ships of the Navie that muſt, and (if they were reduced) that can recover and maintain Englands honour; It is the Ships of the Navie, and not the Pinaces and Frigates. And then begins to make his recantation, as he thinks and ſaith, That whereas he ſaith the Admiralls, Vice-Admiralls, and Rear-Admiralls, have not ſhot one ſhot in anger, ſince theſe diſtracted Wars began, his intention was, and is, that they have not ſhot one ſhot in anger, <hi>viz.</hi> in offence or defence, in a Warlike manner, againſt any of the Kings Men of War, or any other Ship that hath affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</p>
            <p>Concerning reforming the firſt, ſecond, and third rank-Ships, we have given ſo full an Anſwer already, that we ſhall not need to reiterate it again; Onely in the ten times ſo many Pinaces, and ten times ſo many Frigates, the honour of the Seas cannot be maintained: It is the Ships of Englands Navie (ſaith Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi>) that muſt maintain the honour of the Sea;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113650:19"/>which we agree unto; but not to reduce them into the poſture of Frigates, with one Tire of Ordnance, as Maſter <hi>Burrell</hi> would have them. And as for the Admiralls, Vice-Admiralls, and Rear-Admiralls, That his meaning is, they have not ſhot one ſhot in anger, in offence or defence, in a Warlike manner, againſt the Kings Men of War; He makes the cure worſe then the diſeaſe, and abuſeth not onely that Honourable Lord, but all other Commanders, as if they did not know how to defend themſelves, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend an Enemy, in a Warlike manner.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>NA. BRENT.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113650:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
